Guide to the Baker Family papers, 1853-1976 MS 040
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Capt. James A. Baker Family papers
1853-1976
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Baker, James Addison, 1930-
MS 040
6 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
Family correspondence, scrapbooks, and clippings of the Baker Family, from Captain James A. Baker (appointed Chairman of the Board, Rice Institute, 1891) through attorney James A. Baker, III (Rice Board of Trustees, Trustee Emeretus, 1993 - present). A small portion of the materials relate to the Baker, Botts, Garwood & Parker law firm (later known as Baker Botts law firm).
Biographical Note
Capt. James A. Baker was a prominent attorney in the law firm of Baker, Botts & Baker, who represented many wealthy citizens, one of whom was William Marsh Rice, founder of Rice University. In 1891, Baker was made a member of the Rice Institute Board of Trustees and eventually became Chairman of the Board. After Rices death in 1900, a suspicious Capt. Baker alerted authorities to the possibility of foul play. Because of his efforts, investigators discovered that Rice was in fact murdered by an associate.
As Chairman of the Board, Baker contributed to the establishment of Rice University an elite educational institution. Because of his business savvy, the Rice endowment was more than doubled in the early years of the university. Mr. Baker served as Chairman until his death on Aug. 2, 1941. His son, James A. Baker, Jr., served in World War II, became a lawyer in the family firm and continued the Baker commitment to Rice.
James A. Baker III., Capt. Bakers grandson, was born in 1930 to the wealthy Baker family and attended Princeton University. He joined the military and spent two years as a marine lieutenant. After his stint in the military, Baker attended University of Texas School of Law and began a career as a lawyer which lasted until his wifes death in 1970. At the urging of his friend George H. W. Bush, Baker ran for the Senate. He lost the Senate race, but went on to serve as chief of staff and Secretary of the Treasury in President Ronald Reagans administration and as Secretary of State under George Bush. He has had a hand in the management of every Republican campaign for president from 1976 to 1992. After his career in politics Baker returned to working as an attorney and became a member Baker Botts law firm.
On June 2, 1992, Dr. Richard J. Stoll, Director for the Center for the Study of Institutions and Values, as well as a professor of Political Science, sent a memo to then Rice President George Rupp, suggesting that Rice approach then Secretary of State James A. Baker III for the beginnings of a "James Baker Institute". Rupp responded favorably to Stoll's memo and thus the Baker Institute was born. On March 31, 1993, Secretary Baker gave a speech accepting Rice's offer of an Institute in his honor, laying down his ideas on the Baker Institute. In this speech, entitled Ideas Into Action, in which he charged the Baker Institute to "draw together statesmen, scholars and students...and...build a bridge between the world of ideas and the world of action..." These founding words were later used as the building stones for the external architecture of the building.
The Honorable James A. Baker, III would later served on the Rice Board of Trustees from 1993 to the present day, currently acting as Trustee Emeretus.
Scope and Contents
Family correspondence, scrapbooks, and clippings of the Baker Family, from Captain James A. Baker (appointed Chairman of the Board, Rice Institute, 1891) through attorney James A. Baker, III (Rice Board of Trustees, Trustee Emeretus, 1993 - present). A small portion of the materials relate to the Baker, Botts, Garwood & Parker law firm (later known as Baker Botts law firm).
Access Restrictions
To access this material, patrons must read the Baker Family Archives Agreement and sign a user acknowledgement form. Please see Woodson Research Center staff for assistance.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 1-7 and 9 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586. Box 8 stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center in the vault.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift donated by Texas Commerce Bank and James & Susan Baker, 1984.
Related Materials
See Capt. James A. Baker correspondence, clippings, and photographs collection, 1853-1971, MS 487, Woodson Research Center.
See James A. Baker III Political papers, Princeton University
See Baker Family "Information Files", Woodson Research Center.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business; Law and legislation; Education; Universities and colleges
Document Types
photographs; reports; clippings (information artifacts); corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
Baker, James Addison, 1930-; Baker, Rowena Crawford
Subjects (Corporations)
Baker & Botts.; Rice University.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1853-1971, 255353
  - Rowena Crawford & James A. Baker, 1855, 1859, 255368 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rowena Crawford & James A. Baker, 1861, 255367 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rowena Crawford & James A. Baker, 1862, 255366 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rowena Crawford & James A. Baker, 1863-1868, 255365 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rowena Crawford & James A. Baker, undated, 255364 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family (with related materials), 1853-1878, 255363 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cadet James A. Baker, Texas Military Institute, 1874-1878, 255362 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family and friends, 1912-1921, 255361 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family and friends, 1922-1928, 255360 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Family and friends, 1930-1971, 255359 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (undated), genealogical materials, clippings, 255358 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Expenses for family commencing Jan. 1, 1866" [ledger], 255357 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - James A. Baker Jr.: WWI correspondence, service record, mementos, 255356 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - James A. Baker III: School, camp, 1935-1950, 255355 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Means family deaths, 255354 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series II: Capt. James A. Baker death, 1941, 255348
  - Tributes, resolutions, 255352 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Funeral arrangements, 255351 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Condolences, 255350 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newsclippings, 255349 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series III: Baker, Botts, Garwood & Parker law firm, 1900-1929, 255342
  - Business correspondence (with related materials), 1919-1922, 1927, 255347 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Business correspondence, Aug.-Nov. 1922, 255346 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Memorials to Judge Edwin B. Parker, Dec. 1929, 255345 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Gammel's Table of Cases of all the Texas Reports, 1900, 255344 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Index to suit 198, Easton & Rintoul Trustees et al v. H & TC Ry Co., 255343 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks and mementos, 1876-1957, 255336
  - Capt. James A. Baker 1876, 1915, 255341 (Box 6)
  - James A. Baker, Jr., 1955-1957, 255340 (Box 6)
  - Carmina Princetonia, 255339 (Box 6)
  - Family mementos, 255338 (Box 6)
  - Photographic reproduction of portrait of Anna Bland McRobert, 255337 (Box 6)
  - Condolences scrapbook (3 volumes), 1941 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1934-1940 (Box 7)
  - Framed wedding announcement, 1886 (Box 8)
  - "The Oaks" photographs with binder, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Board of Trustees memoriam, 1941 (Box 8)
  - "Beautiful Paris: Splendors, Mysteries, and People of the Great City" book, 1894 (Box 9)
  - Musical scores, 1910-1930 (Box 9)
  - Army promotion certificate, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1918; 1968 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - News clippings, 1956; 1976 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, 1874-1960 (Box 9, Folder 4)